Let us go then, you and I
When the evening is spread out against the sky
Like a patient etherized upon a table
Let us go through certain half-deserted streets
The muttering retreats
Of restless nights in one-night cheap hotels
And sawdust restaurants with oyster-shells
Streets that follow like a tedious argument
Of insidious intent
To lead you to an overwhelming question
Oh do not ask what is it
Let us go and make our visit
In the room the women come and go
Talking of Michelangelo
The yellow fog that rubs its back upon the window-panes
The yellow smoke that rubs its muzzle on the window-panes
Licked its tongue into the corners of the evening
Lingered upon the pools that stand in drains
Let fall upon its back the soot that falls from chimneys
Slipped by the terrace made a sudden leap
And seeing that it was a soft October night
Curled once about the house and fell asleep
And indeed there will be time
For the yellow smoke that slides along the street
Rubbing its back upon the window-panes
There will be time there will be time
To prepare a face to meet the faces that you meet
There will be time to murder and create
And time for all the works and days of hands
That lift and drop a question on your plate
Time for you and time for me
And time yet for a hundred indecisions
And for a hundred visions and revisions
Before the taking of a toast and tea
In the room the women come and go
Talking of Michelangelo
And indeed there will be time
To wonder do I dare and do I dare
Time to turn back and descend the stair
With a bald spot in the middle of my hair
They will say how his hair is growing thin
My morning coat my collar mounting firmly to the chin
My necktie rich and modest but asserted by a simple pin
They will say but how his arms and legs are thin
Do I dare
Disturb the universe
In a minute there is time
For decisions and revisions which a minute will reverse
For I have known them all already known them all
Have known the evenings mornings afternoons
I have measured out my life with coffee spoons
I know the voices dying with a dying fall
Beneath the music from a farther room
So how should I presume
And I have known the eyes already known them all
The eyes that fix you in a formulated phrase
And when I am formulated sprawling on a pin
When I am pinned and wriggling on the wall
Then how should I begin
To spit out all the butt-ends of my days and ways
And how should I presume
And I have known the arms already known them all
Arms that are braceleted and white and bare
But in the lamplight downed with light brown hair
Is it perfume from a dress
That makes me so digress
Arms that lie along a table or wrap about a shawl
And should I then presume
And how should I begin
Shall I say I have gone at dusk through narrow streets
And watched the smoke that rises from the pipes
Of lonely men in shirt-sleeves leaning out of windows
I should have been a pair of ragged claws
Scuttling across the floors of silent seas
And the afternoon the evening sleeps so peacefully
Smoothed by long fingers
Asleep tired or it malingers
Stretched on the floor here beside you and me
Should I after tea and cakes and ices
Have the strength to force the moment to its crisis
But though I have wept and fasted wept and prayed
Though I have seen my head grown slightly bald brought in upon a platter
I am no prophet and here's no great matter
I have seen the moment of my greatness flicker
And I have seen the eternal Footman hold my coat and snicker
And in short I was afraid
And would it have been worth it after all
After the cups the marmalade the tea
Among the porcelain among some talk of you and me
Would it have been worth while
To have bitten off the matter with a smile
To have squeezed the universe into a ball
To roll it towards some overwhelming question
To say I am Lazarus come from the dead
Come back to tell you all I shall tell you all
If one settling a pillow by her head
Should say that is not what I meant at all
That is not it at all
And would it have been worth it after all
Would it have been worth while
After the sunsets and the dooryards and the sprinkled streets
After the novels after the teacups after the skirts that trail along the floor
And this and so much more
It is impossible to say just what I mean
But as if a magic lantern threw the nerves in patterns on a screen
Would it have been worth while
If one settling a pillow or throwing off a shawl
And turning toward the window should say
That is not it at all
That is not what I meant at all
No I ain't Prince Hamlet never meant to be
I'm more the helpin' kind a quiet deputy
Good for makin' an entrance settin' a scene or two
Sayin' somethin' polite then movin' on through
I play my part don't make a fuss
Glad to serve not one to cuss
Careful with my words and mighty precise
But folks might say I ain't all that concise
Truth be told I've been downright silly
A time or two I've looked plain ol' frilly
I'm gettin' old yeah I surely am
Might just roll up my trousers don't give a damn
Should I part my hair from the back
Do I dare to eat a peach or would that catch me some flack
Maybe I'll slip on them white flannel pants
Go walk the beach slow take my chances with chance
I've heard the mermaids singin' floatin' in tune
Soft like honey 'neath a saltwater moon
But I don't reckon they'd sing for me
I've seen 'em ridin' out there on the waves
Combin' sea foam into silvery braids
Where the wind turns the tide to black and white
And the day fades quiet into southern night
We lingered deep where the sea dreams lie
With sea-girls dressed in red weed and rye
Till voices called us from dry land's frown
And we woke up gaspin' just in time to drown